Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 14 -- Materials held at the University of Pennsylvania 1705-1788 Mss.B.F85inventory14
American Philosophical Society
- Correspondence (University of Pennsylvania), 1758-1788
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 March 30; A.L.S. 3p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Question of duties on goods sent to America. Desires a letter of recommendation to the President of the Congress for his Uncle [John Williams], who is about to sail, stating that he has not been employed by the English King since his commission in America, ten years ago; that he has been in France eighteen months and that Dr. Franklin wishes him to be received by his countrymen.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 March 31; A.L.S. 1p.; Sarsfield, Guy-Claude, comte de
    Desiring to know the whereabouts of a M. d'Orbrais, who went to America on a mission for Dr. Franklin; gave him a commission also, but has heard nothing from him.
  - Appendix, 1780 March 31; A.L.S. 4p.; Morris, Robert. Philadelphia
    The high esteem in which he holds both [Silas] Deane and Dr. Franklin; Considers the former a marty to the cause of America; his own embittering experience as a public officer.
  - Appendix, 1780 April 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Concerning the shipment of supplies a Brest. Report that the State of Maryland had taken some notice of him, as regards the management of their funds in England; desires further particulars.
  - Appendix, 1780 April 12; L.S. 2p.; James Arthur Degge, et al., of the "Alliance." On board the "Alliance," L'Orient
    Stating their destitute condition; have received neither wages nor prize-money; their debts unpaid, and the ship almost ready to sail.
  - Appendix, 1780 April 14; L.S. 3p.; Jacob Nuter, et al., of the crew of the "Alliance." L'Orient
    Petition to have their wages and prize-money paid in France, rather than in America.
  - Appendix, 1780 April 18; L.S. 2p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. Passy
    Stating what rights the two privateers, the "Monsieur" and "La Grandville" have in the distribution of prizes.
  - Appendix, 1780 April 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Forwards a list of articles sent to Brest for shipment.
  - Appendix, 1780 April 22; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    News from America, [Gen. Sir Henry] Clinton has at last appeared in South Carolina. Fears for the fate of the "Mercury" which bore Dr. Franklin's despatches. The Farmers General to make an arrangement with the writer corcerning duties.
  - Appendix, 1780 May 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Useless to send any more clothing to Brest, until transportation to America can be secured.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 May 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Asking him to procure the exchange of a solitary English prisoner who was left out of the cartels.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 May 16; A.L.S. 2p.; Rousseau, Jean. Geneva
    Desires a reply to his former letter, enclosing a memorial on the subject of American Independence.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 May 19; L.S. James Lovell and W[illia]m Churchill Houston. 1p.; Huntington, Samuel
    Resolution concerning draft on Dr. Franklin and [John] Jay. Extract from the Minutes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 May 20; A.L.S. 4p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Discusses ways and means of shipping the supplies for the American army; poor quality of French shoes. Report from Philadelphia that up to March 18th, General [Sir Henry] Clinton had done nothing; the American force opposed to him numbered 7,000.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 May 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Objecting to the order of the French Government to pay export duties; desires such explanations made as will free him from payment. Capt. Kendrick, a prisoner, wishes his board paid so that he may return to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 May 31; L.S. 3p.; James Warren, et al., of the "Alliance." L'Orient
    Asking for their wages and prize-money and requesting to have their ship sent back to America; begs to know the answer to Dr. Franklin's memorial to the Court of Denmark, concerning the prize-vessels. Regretting that Capt. [Pierre] Landais is deprived of his command as his offense, as charged, reflects seriously upon his officers.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 1; L. 3p.; J. Watkins, et al., of the crew of the "Alliance." L'Orient
    Sending an impudent paper, signed by 115 men of the "Alliance," in which they demand their prize-money and Capt. Pierre Landais's restoration to his command.
  - Appendix, 1780 June 5; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Advising the purchase of a ship to carry the stores of America.
  - Appendix, 1780 June 7; L.S. 2p.; James Arthur Degge, et al., of the " Alliance." L'Orient
    Asking to have Capt. [Pierre] Landais restored to the command of the "Alliance."
  - Appendix, 1780 June 9; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Enclosing a petition from some French merchants who are charged with giving an erroneous estimate on tobacco shipped to them; desires him to sanction the petition and sent it to M. [Jacques] Necker.
  - Appendix, 1780 June 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Destouches, -----. Dunkirk
    Transmits a copy of the Admiralty Proceedings upon the prizes "Le Pierre" and "L'Amité" taken by the American corsair, the "Black Prince."
  - Appendix, 1780 June 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Capt. [John Paul] Jones gone to Paris with news of the revolution on board the "Alliance." The "Serapis'' to be sold; question of the French Govenment buying it and permitting it to be used to send supplies to America.
  - Appendix, 1780 June 16; L.S. 2p.; Landais, Capt. Pierre. L'Orient
    Has resumed command of the "Alliance"; sends a copy of his commission to show that he is within his rights; asks for orders concerning the arms on board the "Alliance"; offers to execute any commissions for Dr. Franklin in America.
  - Appendix, 1780 June 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Introducing Dr. John Foulke and Mr. [George] Fox, of Philadelphia.
  - Appendix, 1780 June 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Capt. [John Paul] Jones can regain the "Alliance" only be capture; question of transporting the 4,000 suits of clothes. Arrival of Marquis de la Fayette in Boston.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 July 31; L.S. 1p.; Vergennes, Charles Gravier, comte de. Versailles
    Concerning the correspondence between himself and Mr. [John] Adams; desires it transmitted to Congress in order that they may judge of Mr. Adams's fitness for his present delicate mission.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June-July?; A.L. 5p.; de Kloguene, Denis-Nicolas Cottineau
    Concerning certain observations of John Paul Jones, printed in the Gazette of Amsterdam and Leyden, relative to the encounter between the American ships and the English frigates, the "Serapis" and the "Countess of Scarborough"; contradicts many of Jones's statements; condemns his plan of battle and his treatment of the wounded.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 August 3; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    No word from [Le Ray] de Chaumont concerning the purchase of the ship at Bordeaux. Promises to delay drawing bills as much as possible.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 August 28; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Introducing Jeremiah Allen, of Boston.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 August 29; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Introducing Mrs. William Blake, of South Carolina, and her children, and asking for passports to England for them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Fournier, Simon-Pierre, la jeune
    Asking him to appoint a convenient time to go and hear the organ.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 26; A.L.S. 3p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Detailed account of loading a ship at l'Orient with a cargo, including saltpetre, destined for America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 September 28; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Requesting a passport for George Moore, son of Philip Moore, of Philadelphia, who wishes to visit his grandfather in the Isle of Man.
  - Appendix, 1780 September 30; A.L.S. 3p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Question of how to transfer the saltpetre from St. Malo to l'Orient, for shipment on the "Breton." Capt. Samson returned without doing anything. Extravagant ideas about the money to be borrowed in Europe.
  - Appendix, 1780 October 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Ship being loaded as quickly as possible. Desires the return of papers relative to the Spanish snow being recaptured by the "Hercules," Capt. [John] Carey.
  - Appendix, 1780 October 10; A.L.S. 3p.; Stiles, Ezra. Newport
    Sends drawings and descriptions of a new wheel for a grist mill, invented by Mr. Kelsy, of Connecticut. Spirited account of Gen. [Benedict] Arnold's treason.
  - Appendix, 1780 October 13; A.L.S. 2p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. L'Orient
    Description of a tremendous storm; his vessels unable to proceed to America for some time; the supplies for the United States to be carefully preserved; great courage displayed by the crew; enclosing an account of the storm, by the officers of the "Ariel" [2p.].
  - Appendix, 1780 October 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Introducing Mr. French, of Bordeaux. Anxious to hear of the great ship's arrival at l'Orient.
  - Appendix, 1780 October 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Introducing M. Zoilcoffre, a Swiss, who has been for some time in America.
  - Appendix, 1780 October 17; A.L.S. 6p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Plan for utilizing the Massachusetts State ship, "Mars," now at Nantes. Desires advice concerning the Portuguese Captain who was taken by Capt. [Simon] Samson. News of [John Paul] Jones's disaster; this makes more goods to be shipped.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 October 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Question of shipping the saltpetre. News of the check Gen. [Horatio] Gates has received.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 October 24; A.L.S. 3p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    M. [Le Ray] de Chaumont's failure to pay his bills imminent; the writer's own credit must be maintained at whatever cost; begs Dr. Franklin to see that all of his notes are promptly honored.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 October 31; A.L.S. 3p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Sorry that Dr. Franklin has the gout. The "Mars" soon to be loaded. All difficulties concerning the saltpetre to be removed. Promises to send accounts in a day or two.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1780.] November 21; A.L. 2p.; -----, -----
    Question of the genuineness of certain bills. The heads of the British apparently turned by their success in South Carolina and by their acquisition of Gen. [Benedict] Arnold; seven-eighths of them in favor of continuing the war; belief that the Americans will quarrel with their allies. Trail of an American, named [John] Trumbull, for treason; belief that he will be convicted merely because he is of the same rank as the late Major [John] André.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 9; L.S. 1p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Invoice of fifty-six pieces of artillery shipped from Bordeaux to l'Orient on Dr. Franklin's order.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 21; L.S. S[amuel] Huntington, President. 1p.; Huntington, Samuel
    Orders concerning the release and exchange of Henry Laurens.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 December 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Announcing the birth of a daughter.
  - Appendix, [1780.]; A.N. 1p.; Chaumont, Jacques-Donatien Le Ray de
    Computation of the cost of clothing 15,000 men. (In French.)
  - Appendix, 1780; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Josselin, Laurent
    Has lost his position in the Royal Arsenal at Marseilles; anxious to secure work with the army in America.
  - Appendix, 1780; A.L.S. 1p.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834
    Sending him an "arrét" just received for their free ports.
  - Appendix, A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Asking his influence on behalf of Lieurenant-Colonel [Antoine Felix] Wuibert, of the American army, who has suffered imprisonment and hardship; his appointments never paid him.
  - Appendix, 1780; A.L.S. 2p.; Soulavie, L'Abbé Jean Louis Giraud
    Has an unpublished work on the American Revolution, which has been praised by Comte de Vergennes. He sends Dr. Franklin a list of questions, and desires permission to publish his answers.
  - Appendix, 1781 January 4; L.S. Sam[ue]l Huntington, President. 1p.; Huntington, Samuel
    Enclosing an order of Congress [IV, 66] for the release and exchange of Henry Laurens.
  - Appendix, 1781 January 16; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Concerning a draft drawn by him on [Le Ray] de Chaumont and protested; money needed by him in case M. de Chaumont did not resume payment; his reputation as a merchant involved; enclosing list of his bills drawn on Dr. Franklin [1p.].
  - Appendix, 1781 January 18; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Concerning a draft on Dr. Franklin given by him to M. Carier to replace certain drafts on [Le Ray] de Chaumont.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 25; A.L.S. 4p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    [Le Ray] de Chaumont approaching bankruptcy; before this occurs advises the purchase from him of a goods ready for America. The ship at Bordeaux to be forced to go to l'Orient,
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 27; A.L.S. 3p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Information received in a letter from Joseph Wharton, that Col. [John] Laurens is appointed Envoy Extraordinary to Paris, on Particular business only; Mr. [William] Palfrey coming as Consul-General of France. Prisoners captured by the Americans.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 February 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Desiring to know what answer to make to the priosoners who are continually begging to be exchaged. Encloses a letter for M. [Jacques] Necker.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 February 4; A.L.S. 3p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    The ship, " Marquis de la Fayette," not yet at l'Orient. The "Aurora" illegally detained at l'Orient, for freight charges. Glad [Le Ray] de Chaumont has resumed payment.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 February 9; A.L.S. 3p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Concerning the arrest of Mark Anthony, the writer's black servant; encloses certificate of emancipation and asks that appliaction be made to the French Ministers to secure the relase.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 February 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Enclosing a letter just received by the brig "Sally"; the English fleet still in Gardiner's Bay [New York] and the French in Rhode Island.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 February 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Concerning a convey for the vessel "Marquis de la Fayette," which will soon be freighted for America. A consul much needed at Nantes, in order to enlist American seamen in the American service.
  - Appendix, 1781 February 27; D.S. Cha[rle]s Thomson, Sec[retar]y. 2p.; Huntington, Samuel
    Resolutions complimentary to John Paul Jones.
  - Appendix, 1781 February 29; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Concerning his protest against freight duty charged on the cargo of the "Aurora." Has his servant [Mark Anthony] back but is under bonds to send him away in six months; complains bitterly of the Procureur's attitude in this affair.
  - Appendix, 1781 March 1; D.S. Cha[rle]s Thomson, Sec[retar]y. 1p.; Huntington, Samuel
    Accession of Maryland to the Confederation of States.
  - Appendix, 1781 March 2; L.S. Sam[uel] Huntington, President. 1p.; Huntington, Samuel
    Enclosing extracts from the minutes of Congress [February 27, 1781], and instructing Dr. Franklin to communicate them to the King of France.
  - Appendix, 1781 March 6; L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Sends a copy of an account [1p.] received from l'Orient, contradicting the reported mutiny of the Pennsylvania troops, as published by the English.
  - Appendix, 1781 March 13; A.L.S. 2p.; Parke, Matthew. L'Orient
    On behalf of the officers and men of the "Alliance," urges the payment of the prize-money due them; the present Commander of the "Alliance," [Capt. John Barry], much liked.
  - Appendix, 1781 March 20; A.L.S. 3p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    The ship, "Marquis de la Fayette," ready to sail for America after the equinox; awaits Dr. Franklin's final orders as to her destination.
  - Appendix, 1781 April 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    The "Marquis de la Fayette" and the "Alliance" have just sailed; the despatches to be sent by the "Aurora."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 April 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Deane, Silas. Paris
    Encloses a letter from Mr. [Arthur] Lee; has promised that his board-bill shall be paid; would not trouble Dr. Franklin with this matter if his own circumstances were different.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 April 18; A.L.S. 4p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Is coming to Passy. Recently travelled with [Thomas] Paine, the author of "Common Sense"; Paine's opinion of [Silas] Deane and [Arthur] Lee. Advantage of sending cloth to America to be made up into uniforms.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 May 18; A.L.S. 2p.; Franklin, William Temple
    Concerning an action which took place on May 2d between the French squadron and an English fleet, from St. Eustatius, of thirty-four merchant vessels, escorted by the "Vengeance" and other ships; twenty-two merchant vessels and two corsairs taken.
    (In French and English.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 June 6; L.S. 3p.; Morris, Robert. Philadelphia
    Announcing his appointment as Minister of Finance; undertakes the work at a great sacrifice of his domestic happiness; Dr. Franklin's support will be highly esteemed; aware that anyone in a high station must be subject to bitter attacks.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 June 8; L.S. 3p.; Robert Morris, S.J. of Finances. Philadelphia
    Concerning the choice of a firm to receive the money granted by France to the United States; in favor of selecting Messrs. Couteulx and Co.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 June 14; D.S. Cha[rle]s Thomson, Sec[retar]y. 1p.; Huntington, Samuel
    Resolution empowering Dr. Franklin to offer Lieut-Gen. [John] Burgoyne in exchange for the Honorable Henry Laurens.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 June 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Tardy, Gabriel, Nantes
    News received of the escape of Capt. [Gustavus] Cunningham and others from Mill Prison. On June 4th, twenty-four Americans entered the British service.
  - Appendix, 1781 July 5; L.S. Sam[uel] Huntington, President. 2p.; Huntington, Samuel
    Empowering Dr. Franklin to offer Lieut-Gen. [John] Burgoyne in exchange for the Honorable Henry Laurens.
  - Appendix, 1781 July 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Daniel of St. Thomas Jenifer. Philadelphia
    Asking that the enclosed letter from Mr. Lowndes to his son, be forwarded to London. Dr. Franklin unanimously chosen Peace Commissioner; appointment of [Henry] Laurens unnecessary.
  - Appendix, 1781 July 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Bache, Sarah. Philadelphia
    Introducing the bearer, Major [David Salisbury] Franks, of the American Army, to Dr. Franklin's notice and friendship.
  - Appendix, 1781 July 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Morris, Robert. Philadelphia
    Desiring Dr. Franklin to sound some of the eminent bankers in Paris, as to the credit they are willing to give to a United States bank founded upon the enclosed plan.
  - Appendix, 1781 July 21; A.L.S. 3p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    A plan by which British prisoners may be procured and exchanged for Americans.
  - Appendix, 1781 July 13,14,19,21; L.S. 13p.; Robert Morris, S.J. of Finances. Philadelphia
    Deplorable state of the country's finances due to the use of paper money. Money needed to start a bank and a Mint. Mr. [John] Jay instructed to negotiate a large loan at Madrid. Unfair to ask France for more money. Desiring Dr. Franklin to confer with leading bankers in Paris as to organizing a National Bank in America. Advising that the money loaned by France should remain in that country. Attempts made by Congress to raise the value of paper money.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 August 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Trumbull, Jonathan. Hartford
    Sends money for the use of his son [Col. John Trumbull], then a prisoner in London.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 August 4; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Sends letters for Dr. Franklin which arrived on the brig "Sally," from Rhode Island.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 August 10; A.L.S. 3p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Purchase of cannon. Capture of a cutter in the Bay of Biscay, by two American privateers. An American vessel from Port-au-Prince chased on shore by a British vessel and totally wrecked.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 August 10; D.S. Cha[rle]s Thomson, Sec[retar]y. 1p.; Huntington, Samuel
    Resolution appointing Robert R. Livingston Secretary for Foreign Affairs.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 August 15; A.L.S. 3p.; Burke, Edmund. Charles St. London
    Feels the calamities of the war and among them the discontinuance of his intercourse with Dr. Franklin; has desired his friendship for a long time. Concerning the reported application of Congress for the return of his friend, Gen. [John] Burgoyne, to captivity in America; appeals to Dr. Franklin not to suffer this injustice to take place.
    Printed in Burke's Speeches, II, p. 468.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 August 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Submits a proposal for the sale of arms; if he accepts the offer, asks to be appointed Agent.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 August 20; L.S. 3p.; Companie, Mauger et. Metz
    Ready to ship a large amount of goods to the United States; beg that the French importation laws may be waived, in order to facilitate the shipment. Letter from Estris de Cornie endorsing this request.
    A. E. urging that this request be granted. S. B[enjamin] Franklin.
  - Appendix, 1781 September 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Desires a recommentation to M. de Fleury. Has tried to repay Dr. Franklin's favors by turning over business to Mr. [Richard] Bache's house.
  - Appendix, 1781 September 4; L.S. 3p.; J. Cottin and fils Jauge. Paris
    Threatened with the loss of an American bill; appeal to secure its payment.
  - Appendix, 1781 September 5; A.L.S. 4p.; Besse, Jacques. Kehl
    Technical letter from a young printer. Enthusiastic over a perpetual motion machine, which he is planning.
  - Appendix, 1781 September 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Montfort, Comte de
    Recommending Gourlet Duplessis; account of the good services he has rendered the United States; certificates from army officers enclosed.
  - Appendix, 1781 September 13; A.L.S. 2p.; Mallet, -----. Havre
    On his recommendation, trusted William Williams and Augustin Morice; both have departed without paying their room-rent; sends the bill to him for payment.
  - Appendix, 1781 September 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Introducing Wanton Casey, son of Silas Casey, of Rhode Island.
  - Appendix, 1781 September 14; L.S. 1p.; Morris, Robert. Philadelphia
    Commission to procure him certain books on the public account.
  - Appendix, 1781 September 23; L.S. 1p.; Palteau, Chevalier de Veimerange. Paris
    Question of sending supplies to the Agent of Congress, in Boston.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 24; Mem. 2p.; The Continental Congress et al
    Major Lomagne, of Col. [Charles] Armand's Legion, given an honorable discharge on account of illness. Testimony of Gen. Edward Hand, Baron von Steuben and Gen. [John Peter Gabriel] Muhlenberg to Major Lomagne's zeal and activity.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 September 25; L.S. 2p.; Turgot, Etienne François, marquis (brother of baron). Chateau de Bous
    Begging Dr. Franklin to secure from John Hancock an order for the shipment of certain seeds promised the writer by a Frenchman in Pennsylvania.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 October 2; A.L.S. 3p.; Deane, Silas. Paris